Mss.B.W31n
American Philosophical Society
Charles Waterton papers, 1772-1865
Mss.B.W31n
American Philosophical Society
0.25 Linear feet Ca. 145 items
This collection of letters and documents relates primarily to Charles Waterton (B W31n) but included as well are papers of the family (B W31m). Most of the letters to or from Waterton concern birds, bird mating, domestic news, natural history, and Walton Hall, his estate. In addition, there are recipes and a housekeeping account book (1780-1781). There are numerous letters with his sisters-in-law, Eliza and Helen Edmonstone, and also an exchange of letters between Waterton's son Edmund and Sir George Bowyer concerning Papal audiences.
Ca. 145 items.
Waterton, Charles, 1782-1865
Box 1
Biographical/Historical note
Charles Waterton was a British naturalist and ornithologist.
Related Archival Materials note
There are additional Waterton letters in Miscellaneous Ms. Collection; consult the repository.
Early American History Note
This manuscript collection falls outside the geographic scope of the Early American guide (British North America and the United States before 1840). It may be of interest to scholars interested in global history, international relations, imperialism, or the U.S. in the world.
Bowyer, George, Sir, 1811-1883; Charlesworth, Edward P., 1813-1893; Clifford, Walter; Cottrell, Henry; Edmonstone, Eliza; Edmonstone, Helen; Fennell, J. G., (John Greville), 1807-1885; Hobson, Richard, 1795-1868; Jones, Edward; Thackeray, William Makepeace, 1811-1863; Waterton, Edmund, 1830-1887; Account books.; Beyond Early America; Birds.; Home economics -- Accounting -- 18th century.; Natural history.; Ornithology.; Popes.
- Papers
  - Letter to Edwin Green., 9 August, 1862; 11 1/4 x 8 3/4
    Scope and Contents note
    ALS. 4p. Describes journey to Aix-La-Chapelle. Local agriculture.
    General note
    See: See also:
  - Letter to Dawson Turner., 20 December, 1836; 9x7 1/2
    ALS. 3p. Discusses visit to Philadelphia in April 1824, his portrait by C.W. Peale, his book Wanderings, and 2 expeditions to Africa. Mentions Sir Thomas Gage, Charles Butler, Lord Henry Bathurst, Sir Joseph Bank
  - Letter to Edward Charlesworth., 2 December, 1854; 8 3/4x 7 1/4
    ALS. 1p. Recounts an unpleasant encounter while visiting Thomas Baines.
  - Letter to Dawson Turner., 20 December, 1836; 9x7 1/2
    ALS. 3p. Discusses visit to Philadelphia in April 1824, his portrait by C.W. Peale, his book Wanderings, and 2 expeditions to Africa. Mentions Sir Thomas Gage, Charles Butler, Lord Henry Bathurst, Sir Joseph Bank.
  - Letter to Dawson Turner., 20 December, 1836; 9x7 1/2
    ALS. 3p. Discusses visit to Philadelphia in April 1824, his portrait by C. W. Peale, his book Wanderings, and 2 expeditions of Africa. Mentions Sir Thomas Gage, Charles Butler, Lord Henry Bathurst, Sir Joseph Ban
  - Letter to Dawson Turner., 20 December, 1836; 9x7 1/2
  - Letter to Edward Charlesworth., 2 December, 1854; 8 3/4x 7 1/4
  - Letter to [Henry] Denny., 1782-1865; 7 1/2 x 9
    n.d. ALS. 1p. Responds to Hay; will meet at the appointed time.
  - Letter to Dawson Turner., December 20, 1836; 9x7 1/2
    ALS. 3p. Discusses visit to Philadelphia in April 1824, his portrait by C.W. Peale, his book Wanderings, and 2 expeditions to Africa. Mentions Sir Thomas Gage, Charles Butler, Lord Henry Bathurst, Sir Joseph Ban
  - Letter to Edwin Green., 9 August, 1862; 11 1/4 x 8 3/4
  - Letter to Francis Gibson., 24 March, 1848; 9x7 1/4
    ALS. 1p. Forwards parcel and tells of family news.
  - Letter to Edwin Green., 18 November, 1849; 9x7 1/4
    ALS. 1p. Concerns a mysterious sickness among Waterton's trees.
  - Letter to [Henry] Denny., 1782-1865; 7 1/2 x 9
  - Letter to [Richard Hobson?], 1782-1865; 8-3/4x7-1/4
    Walton Hall, Monday morning. A.L.S. 1p. Friendly letter. his attempt at doctoring a friend who is visiting.
  - Letter to "Sir"., 1 July, 1858; 5 3/4x 7 1/4
    ALS. 1p. Extends invitation.
  - Letter to Henry Smurthwaithe., 11 December, 1854; 10x8
    ALS. 1p. Responds to an inquiry about the breeding of Nightingales.
  - Letter to Edwin Green., 11 April, 1858; 8 3/4x7 1/4
    ALS. 1p. Travel plans. Mentions Westerman and Ogden.
  - Letter to Dawson Turner., 20 December, 1836; 9x7 1/2
  - Letter to Henry Smurthwaithe., 11 December, 1854; 10x8
  - Letter to Edwin Green., 18 November, 1849; 9x7 1/4
  - Letter to Henry Smurthwaithe., 11 December, 1854; 10x8
  - Letter to Samuel Taylor., 5 July, 1845; 9 3/4 x 8
    ALS. 1p. Acknowledges receipt of Taylor's plan to "repel intruders from your trees".
  - Letter to "Sir"., 7 April, 1849; 9x7 1/4
    ALS. 1p. Waterton declines offer to buy author's specimens for his museum.
  - Letter to Dawson Turner., 20 December, 1836; 9x7 1/2
  - Letter to Dawson Turner., 20 December, 1836; 9x7 1/2
  - Letter to A. Vogue., 28 April, 1864; 9x7 1/2
    ALS. 1p Responds to a request for an item by saying its not important.
  - Letter to Edwin Green., August 9, 1862; 11 1/4 x 8 3/4
    ALS. 4P. Describes journey to Aix-La-Chapelle. Local agriculture.
  - Letter to Edward Charlesworth., 2 December, 1854; 8 3/4 x 7 1/4
    ALS. 1p. Recounts an unpleasant encounter while visiting Thomas Baines. 1. Baines, Thomas, 1822-1875. I. Charlesworth, ard.
  - Letter to Francis Gibson., 24 March, 1848; 9x7 1/4
    ALS. 1p. Forwards parcel and tells of family news. 1. Waterton, Edmund, 1830-1887. I. Gibson, Francis 1753-1805.
  - Letter to Edwin Green., 18 November, 1849; 9x7 1/4
    ALS. 1p. Concerns a mysterious sickness among Waterton's trees. 1. Siliviculture. I. Green, Edwin.
  - Letter to Edwin Green., 11 April, 1858; 8 3/4x7 1/4
    ALS. 1p. Travel plans. Mentions Westerman and Ogden. 1. Ogden, John. 2. Westerman,. I. Green, Edwin.
  - Letter to Edwin Green., 9 August, 1862; 11 1/4 x 8 3/4
    ALS. 4p. Describes journey to Aix-La-Chapelle. Local agriculture. 1. King Victor Emmanuel II of Sardinia, 1820-1878. 2. Garribaldi, Giuseppe, 1807-1882. 3. Waterton, Edmund, 1830. 4. Aachen--Travel
  - Letter to Edwin Green ..., 9 August, 186
    and Description. I. Green, Edwin.
  - Letter to [Richard Hobson?], 1782-1865; 8-3/4x7-1/4
    Walton Hall, Monday morning. A.L.S. 1p. Friendly letter. His attempt at doctoring a friend who is visiting.
  - Letter to Henry Smurthwaithe., 11 December, 1854; 10x8
    ALS. 1p. Responds to an inquiry about the breeding of Nightingales. 1. Pilkington, Sir William, 1758-1848. 2. Nightingales. I. Smurthwaithe,.
  - Letter to Samuel Taylor., 5 July, 1845; 9 3/4x 8
    ALS. 1p. Acknowledges receipt of Taylor's plan to "repel intruders from your trees". I. Taylor, Samuel, f1. 1800-1820.
  - Letter to Dawson Turner., 20 December, 1836; 9x7 1/2
    ALS. 3p. Dicusses visit to Philadelphia in April 1824, his portrait by C.W. Peale, his book Wanderings, and 2 expeditions to Africa. Mentions Sir Thomas Gage, Charles Butler, Lord Henry Bathurst, Sir Joseph Bank
  - Letter to Dawson Turner ...
    1. Banks, Sir Joseph, 1743-1820. 2. Bathurst, Lord Henry, 1762-1834. 3. Butler, Charles, 1750-1832. 4. Gage, Sir Thomas, 1721-1787. 5. Turner, Elizabeth. 6. Peale, Charles Willson, 1741-1827. 7. Africa--Travel and Exploration. 8. Truner, Dawson, 1775-
  - Letter to Dawson Turner ..., 20 December, 1858
  - Letter to "Madam"., 5 July, 1837; 9x8
    ALS. 1p. Concerning delivery of a large lobster specimen and his future travel plans.
  - Letter to "Sir"., 26 January, 1842; 9x7 1/2
    ALS. 1p. Declines an offer of membership into a scientific society.
  - Letter to "My dear Miss Eliza;", April 4, 1844; 9x7-1/4
    Walton Hall, A.L.S. 1p. Friendly letter. Forwards autograph. News of relatives, and of his foot being being hurt while a tree bole was being moved.
  - Letter to "Sir"., 7 April, 1849; 9x7 1/4
    ALS. 1p. Waterton declines offer to buy author's specimens for his museum. 1. Taxiderm
  - Letter to "Sir"., 1 July, 1858; 5 3/4x 7 1/4
    ALS. 1p. Extends invitation. 1. Hobson, Richard, 1795-1868.
  - Letter to A. Vogue., 28 April, 1864; 9x7 1/2
    ALS. 1p. Responds to a request for an item by saying its not important. I. Vogue, A
  - Letters of scientists: William Orr, Prof. Henslow, Robert Chambers, W.Pettigrew, Richard Owen, Nathaniel Ogle, R. Stephenson, C.W. Williams, Thomas Woolner, Alexander Gilchrist, Albert Way, F. W. Fairholt, Charles Manby, George Rutledge, John Allen, Charles Waterton and Mr. Nichols: also, a poem on evolution, 1833-1873
    D. 15 items. Various sizes.
  - Letter to Francis Gibson., 24 March, 1848; 9x7 1/4
  - Letter to Edwin Green., 9 August, 1862; 11 1/4 x 8 3/4
  - Letter to Edwin Green., 11 April, 1858; 8 3/4x7 1/4
  - Letter to Mr. Nichols., undated; Waterton, Charles, 1782-1865
    Immediate Source of Acquisition note
    1977 1301.a ms